You read a lot today about the
billion-dollar one-person company. Do
you buy into that? Basically, someone,
you know, AI can just, you know, like
code their way into getting to, you
know, 10 million, 20 million, 30 million
dollars in in revenue and then create
this massive company. I think that's a
lie.
>> Hello, I'm your host David Bernard. My
guest today is Kenneth Schlenker,
co-founder and CEO of Opal, the Focus
Company.
On the podcast, I talked with Kenneth
about why retention is the only real
note, how dropping paid conversion from
20% to 9% increased revenue,
and why he sees the rise in competition
as a net positive for Opal.
Hey Kenneth, it's so great to have you
back on the podcast.
>> Thanks so much for having me back.
>> So, we've got a lot to catch up on. You
know, last time we spoke, you were at 5
million in ARR. You since shared that
you hit 10 million in ARR pretty soon
after that. So, you were scaling
rapidly, and now hit over a million
daily active users. So, I mean, the app
has just been taking off. So, I wanted
to talk through some of that with you
and and, you know, see see what it's
taken to get there. So, yeah, tell me
first about like what it took from last
we spoke at 5 million to get to that 10
million.
>> Yeah, it sounds uh
now now long time ago, but yeah, we had
a great conversation last time. Uh we're
really in the process of scaling with at
the time a hard B2B, and we uh we got
to, you know, scale pretty efficiently
with a small team. I think we reached 10
million dollars in ARR with like like 11
people back then. But, you know, after
that, what happened was we weren't
growing as fast as we'd like in terms of
users. And, you know, for us, what what
really matters is to be able to uh
create a product that can be used by
lots of people uh because we're
addressing this massive issue. And so,
you know, we stopped kind of focusing on
on on revenue. We really focusing on
like what product can we build that can
can be a billion user product. And so,
that's the trajectory that changed and
happy to talk about about the stuff that
we've done to to get there.
>> Yeah, you know, one of the things
you you just did a great talk at Tokyo
App Growth Annual last week and you
know, I got to hang out a little bit in
Tokyo.
One of the things you shared in that
talk was that you had a mind shift
mindset shift from efficiency to company
building. Tell tell me a little bit
about that.
>> Yeah, you know, I think this is maybe a
counterintuitive take, but you know, you
see you read a lot today about the
billion-dollar, you know, one-person
company. If you buy into that, basically
someone, you know, AI can just you know,
they could their way into to getting at
to, you know, 10 million, 20 million,
100 million dollars in in revenue and
then, you know, create this massive
company. I I think that's a lie. I think
that actually the companies that
actually do
uh reach a billion people and billions
of valuations, they need more than than
one person. They actually need a team.
Uh you need you need a brand. You need
you need retention and AI can be used to
kind of improve uh the value that uh the
product gives to users and then and only
then I think you can really kind of
create massive massive amounts of value.
And so, yeah, I think that was the topic
of the talk
which which I gave at the conference. I
think, you know, a lot of the apps that
we see today, they're coming online and
I I love you the entrepreneur. You'll
you know, kind of read us also seeing
lots of people they're being able to
create new stuff. But I think also it's
important that people understand that uh
there needs to be more than that to be
able to build massive companies. And so,
that's the that's the shift that we've
been on where, you know, what we want to
do is we want to make sure we can create
a product that is on path to to be a
billion user product. And so, you know,
starts with a team, like figuring out
the right kind of team,
building a brand, building a product
that has a lot of retention, and then
figuring out how to actually use AI to
improve the value we give to users.
>> Yeah, a quote from your talk that I
really loved was teams create product
soul. You can't buy code a brand. I love
that. Like what what's your thinking
there?
>> Yeah, you know, I think maybe sometimes
people think that apps are just like,
you know, tools, but actually people
want to connect with the apps that they
use. They want to they want to feel
something. So, you know, brand is super
important. I think some of the best, you
know, apps out there like have have this
soul in them. And I think that in order
to to have that soul, you really need
kind of people
>> [snorts]
>> that are really caring about this. And
you know, this have like to have a it
doesn't have to be a lot of people. You
know, some some very small teams
create like really soulful products. But
I think that a recipe for for for
failure in my mind is to create
something that has a function, which AI
does really well. I can basically
create, you know, note-taking app. You
can create like calendar apps. Create
like whatever you want. That's just a
function.
And but, you know, you need more than
that to be able to be successful in my
mind.
>> Yeah, and and one last AI take before we
kind of move on back to like more Opal
specific stuff. What are your thoughts
on
people saying AI is going to eat all of
consumer apps? That you know, you seen
this. I mean, competition for in the
screen time space is huge. And then AI
has unlocked the ability to spin up a
screen time app quicker than ever. And
that's actually a popular category that
I see a ton of Indies launching into.
So, how do you think about the way
that's going to impact Opal's business?
And then how do you think that's going
to impact the app economy more broadly?
>> Yeah, there's a lot of there's a lot of
screen time apps here since we went on
There was someone on the podcast.
Actually, someone came to the conference
last week and and walked up to me and
said, you know, that
she was super inspired by Opal and and
that created her own version
of a screen time app and I think it's
one of the, you know, kind of very
popular categories
these days. The thing is that you First
of all, I think what the way I see
competition is a thing that it's it's
actually a net positive for us. I think
what it does is it helps, you know, more
people realize that this problem is
real, educate the market, get more
people to use apps and there's, you
know, there's 5 billion people in the
world that have a smartphone and maybe
today
probably, you know, give or take a few
dozen million that have used a screen
time app or using a screen time app. So,
there's still, you know, kind of massive
opportunity to grow. I think the
challenge is problem is that when um
a lot of these apps are actually kind of
copying, you know, existing existing
stuff. So, instead of trying to to to
build out new categories and and kind of
reach out to newer
kinds of people, you know, they're
they're they're limiting themselves by
by just copying what exists. And so, you
know, in my line, like the biggest
challenge for screen time is
if I walk down the street and I talk to
10 people in any city, could be, you
know, in Texas and
in New York, wherever wherever it is,
and I ask people, you know, random set
of people like, "Do you spend too much
time on your phone?" Everybody will say,
you know, yes or maybe like eight out of
10, right? But then if the next question
is, "There's an app, right? Would you
download this app to help you?" Um
today, you'd lose a lot of people
because a lot of people say, "What do
you mean an app to what to do? How do I
manage How does it help me manage my
screen time? Is it going to be blocking
apps? Like that's crazy. That's not
really something that I want to do." And
so, the problem that I think we need to
to to address as a as a category is
like, how do we actually create
something that these people can use
that's not, you know, what Opal already
does, but that's like what, you know,
other things. And that's really what
we're we're trying to build for for
Opal, which is like figuring out how we
can make it so much easier to to use a
screen time app, no setup required, and
that it's not just about restriction,
that it's really about being able to
kind of coach you in your day-to-day.
So,
that's kind of a long-winded answer, but
I think that, you know, I applaud like
competition. I think it it helps
educate the market, but I think it's
also, you know, the opportunity is is
much larger, and it's it's going to
require innovation and new kinds of apps
and completely new kinds of UI that
you're probably not going to get by
just, you know, typing in, you know, in
cloud like, you know, make an Opal copy
in in 5 minutes, right?
>> Yeah, and you know, we we've seen this
play out for years, even without AI
coding.
It, you know, it's not that hard. The
engineering side is is a lot of hours,
but it's not some insurmountable thing,
and it never has been. And so, you know,
you look at some of the big categories
like a language learning, you know,
Duolingo, despite the recent, you know,
setback in its stock price, is still a
multi-billion dollar company making over
a billion dollars a year. And then you
look at that category, and there are
just so many apps, and huge ones, you
know, Babbel is is massive, you know,
right up there nipping on their heels.
And so, I I I I think, you know, for the
broader industry, and then for Opal
specifically, you're still going to have
category winners like Opal that are like
the brand in the space, even if there
are hundreds of apps that do the same
thing.
And to your point earlier, it's like,
yeah, you can copy Opal pretty, you
know, or easier than ever to copy
aspects of Opal, but you you can't copy
the soul. You can't copy the taste that
went into it. And and as people
experiment with these apps, they'll
probably be hungry for more, and then go
looking for the best app to do it. And I
think, you know, Opal as kind of the the
the leader in the space and as you've
grown the team and improved the product,
it just becomes this like momentum
that isn't going to get stopped by 200
more people by coding in other screen
time app.
>> Yeah, I mean, I I can I bring you in my
next investor pitch? I love that.
>> [laughter]
>> No, I I I fully believe it. And then one
more thing is, you know, we talked about
what happened, you know, since the last
podcast and one of the things I
mentioned is that we had a hard day.
Well, now we're truly freemium. So, we
give away the product for free. And
that's also something that I think is is
very valuable for us in the long run
because, you know, we're getting to a
point where, you know, we passed a
million DAUs
as as as you said and we're growing
really fast. And it comes to a point
where, you know, people have heard about
the app and they hear it from their
friends. And we see a lot of interesting
dynamics of, you know, students that
are, you know, using it together. We see
interesting dynamics also in the family
world where, you know, you have maybe a
teenage a teenager in the family that's
using the app and actually recommend it
to their parents all the other way
around. And so, all of that makes it,
you know, makes our our position
stronger. And, you know, it's activating
kind of these network effects. And it's
really powered by freemium. And I think
it it's
That's why, you know, I'm very confident
in in the future of consumer apps in
general. I think when you when you have
a great product that has retention, that
has a great brand, you're in an
excellent position. And I think what you
can do on top of that is you can either
use artificial intelligence to actually
improve this product. And by improving
this product, what I mean is not saying
just moving the metric metrics. It's
really like, how do you actually really
improve the value that you give to
users? And if you're very confident the
value that you give to users, that
whether it's like giving them time back,
which is kind of what we do, or making
more productive, or whether it's
you helping going to learn language, you
can actually use AI to make that better
and that really will make your product a
lot a lot stronger. And so, I think you
know, it's interesting and I'm sure you
see this all the time maybe in the
public markets at least you know, the
the the apps software you know, SAS of
course and and also some consumer
software is getting really it gets
punished by the market to say hey,
they're not kind of AI native. But I
think that it's it's a bit of an I I
think it's
some misunderstanding of what consumer
apps really are.
It's not just function, it's also
entertainment, it's also something that
people like to do and something that
people love. It's and so you can't just
replace that with an agent or something
else that does it automatically.
>> I wanted to dig a little deeper into the
the switch to freemium cuz that was
a big deal for Apple. You shared a slide
in your presentation
showing that your download to paid
dropped from 20% all the way down to 9%
which sounds super scary to have your
conversion more than cut in half. But
why why did that ultimately end up being
good for the company?
>> No, that we we did that. So we
gave away the product for free. And you
mentioned that you know, our yeah, paid
penetration. So that's how many people
you know, are paying subscribers within
the monthly active users you know, went
from about 20% to to 9% and that's scary
when you when you see this chart, but it
was the right decision. The reason it's
the right decision is because when you
give the product away for free the
people that are using the product become
your marketing. And so what we've seen
as a consequence is also a shift where
we have a lot more organic growth than
we ever have. It's
massively increased and you know, what
we're able to do is we're able to kind
of accelerate this organic growth as
well with some features we can talk
about. Another thing that we've seen is
as a consequence of um a freemium is
that we have a different kind with new
kind user revenue segment that that
exists. I mean, we started with the
segment of I would say professional pros
that are interested in productivity. Uh
you know, people like you and me, people
probably listening to this podcast that
you know, care about their time and and
place a high ROI and like saving time.
So, that was like the initial kind of
segment, but you know, making the app
free really helped us unlock uh students
as a second kind of segment. So, high
school students and college students
were now 2/3 of our uh DAUs are our
students. And what it does is not only
it's great for our mission because we we
know and we really want um you know,
students to be able to build these
healthy habits, healthy digital habits
in their day-to-days. So, that's that's
great for for the mission, but it's also
great uh for organic growth because
students talk about it. And what this
also allowed us to do is now we're
entering kind of a third segment that's
being unlocked where you know, students
basically, especially in high school,
are telling their schools, "Hey, like
you know, instead of taking the phones
away while we're in school, why don't we
why don't you work with Opal to to be
able to create a phone policy?" And so,
now we have also this kind of third
segment uh with schools that's opening.
So, what I would say is um I think that
the freemium strategy is is really
helpful to be able to kind of grow
organically and also kind of unlock uh
unlock new segments that aren't
necessarily, you know, people that would
actually pay upfront for a product. And
so, you know, depends on what you're
looking for, you know, as a as a as an
app founder, you know, whether you're
trying to build uh you know, lifestyle
business. You know, but but if you're
trying to truly create a product that
has um the potential to get used by, you
know, hundreds of millions of people or
a billions of people, which is really
what we think we must do because of the
size of the problem we're facing, then I
think freemium is a really good uh
strategy to get there. Yeah, so to sum
up, we we've seen a decrease in our
conversion to paid, but we've also seen
as a consequence of that an explosion of
our DAUs, and so, you know, and revenue
with it. So, it's a short-term, you
know, scary drop, but what what happens
in the long term is that payback is it
pays back tenfold.
>> That's amazing. Uh I another thing you
did share in that presentation is a
question you ask yourself of where to
draw the line of freemium. And I think
this is a little counterintuitive and
but I think really important to dig
into. So, you you said, "Would a
non-payer recommend the app? If no, give
away more."
Why?
>> Yeah, I think, you know, if you want to
if you want the freemium dynamic to
really pay out, you need to make sure
that the free users are recommending the
app. Um otherwise, that doesn't work. I
think that's a good way to measure the
quality of your freemium product.
Uh you got to figure out whether free
users are going to recommend the app.
And I think that's an issue with a lot
of apps I see where, you know, they're
just kind of giving away a small amount
or
maybe it feels like a trial and then
it's kind of recapped. If you do that,
you're probably not going to benefit
from the organic growth potential of
freemium.
>> Yeah, totally. It's a tough balance of
what to give away and what not to. Were
there were there any like specific tough
calls that y'all made where it's like
this really could should be behind the
paywall, but like it really is such a
good part of the experience that we
don't want to take it away from the free
users. Like what were some of the the
hard decisions and and did you have to
reverse any? Like did you make a bad
call and then reverse it? Or how how did
things go on determining what went into
paid?
>> Yeah, I mean, we've made a lot of
made a lot of mistakes and, you know,
some success. I think the the core is to
measure, you know, experiment and
measure two things. So, you know, the
LTV of of installs, so how people are
converting and paying, and also to
measure the
retention overall, free plus paid,
right? And so, you want to you want to
make sure that you can find the sweet
spot where you're increasing both. It's
really hard. We have this
these
this feature called blocks, so basically
it's you know, you're blocking apps from
9:00 to 10:00 on Monday to Friday,
you're blocking social media for
example. And also, it could be you know,
you put you put together like an open
limit, so that's you know, I can only
open Instagram 10 times
during the day. And so, each of these
are blocks, and so, you know, we we've
experimented with you know, how many
should we give away for free?
You can have one, or you can have two,
or three, or four. And I think today
it's actually three. We've tried many
different approaches, all the way from
like having just one, which is pretty
restrictive, and offering more
and turns out that three
is enough for free users to get a great
experience. They can actually really use
that app, try out a few different
things, and then also, you know, really
kind of power users that are convinced,
you know, will pay because they want
more. So, that's that's one where it
kind of worked out pretty well.
>> Yeah, that's a great example. And and
maybe a way to to think about that,
yeah, it's like the people who are going
to be the heaviest users, you know,
what's the thing that's like most
important to them, and then throttling
it to where the free users still get a
great experience is yeah, is
interesting. I mean, and this
AI is making this so tough with freemium
because you you almost can't give things
away, and it's hard to do a freemium
app. Like I'm I've been I've coding this
app on the side, and I'm I'm working on
this kind of AI coaching feature, and
golly, it can get super expensive.
And and you know, at first I started out
like, oh, I'm going to use like Opus 4.6
cuz it's so much better, and then I was
like, oh, maybe I'll use Sonnet, and
then I was like, "Oh, maybe I'll use
Gemini flash." And uh and it it it's
tough these days to to really draw those
lines and create that great freemium
experience, especially if you're using
AI. But even if you're not using AI,
like it's just such an important place
to really be thoughtful and to do some
experimentation. And you know, like you
said, you didn't just land on three by
magic like guessing it or whatever. You
tried one, you tried five, and and and
you figured it out. And I think that's
what what people need to take away is
like you you just need to try it. And
and for me, like by coding this app,
like I need to see how users actually
use it. Cuz maybe I can, you know, get
away with a better model and more
coaching and things like that. And and
maybe I can do a freemium tier, but I
don't know until I actually get it out
there and start testing it.
>> Yeah, I mean with AI, I think, you know,
the it changes the equation because
you're you're of course paying for the
service of using if you're using a
server-side model, you're paying for
that. So, you need to make sure that,
you know, the the value that you're
creating is actually like higher than of
course like the cost that that you
incur. And I feel like a lot of people,
you know, I think at the beginning I'm
this way, too. You're like, you know,
the value is so cool of all these tools,
you know, you're just going all in and
and building incredible stuff. And then
there's probably like a second phase,
which is wait, like does it make, you
know, economic sense actually? Like, can
I can I charge enough for this? Are
people actually willing Is it good
enough that people are willing to kind
of pay for this on on top? So, it's a
different kind of reality, I guess,
than, you know, when when you were just
making an app that's not that's doesn't
have actually like this kind of marginal
cost on top of it. But yeah, coming back
to I think AI, the interesting it's it's
massively, you know, valuable, I'll say.
And we see some incredible things. I'm
like everyone fully using a lot of these
tools. I think that um every consumer
app is about to have AI, you know,
whether it's fitness app, whether it's
your learning app, finance app, or
screen time app, too. But, I think the
question that
maybe people need to ask is, you know,
how do you actually build an AI that's
on your user's side? And what I mean by
that is, how do we actually build an AI
that actually helps
um deliver more value to users.
And um I think that today
there's not enough people doing that. Um
and so, you know, it's it's not so much
um about I think using AI to
you know, maybe uh trick users into do
doing something. I think it's really has
to come from you What is What is the
exact like core value of like why people
are using my app and how can I make that
a lot better
uh using using AI.
>> Yeah, I'll I'll I'll quote your uh
presentation again, since it's all at
the top of mind. I haven't done a
podcast where like I actually, you know,
saw the podcast guest speak so recent to
the the podcast, but it's kind of fun
cuz I can quote you back to yourself
from the things you really nailed in
your presentation. Um you said, "If your
user wins, you win. That's it." I love
that quote.
>> Yeah, I mean, I think it's you got to I
think it's important to remember that.
We can kind of get caught up with
all that it can do and, you know, add
some fancy features to the app. But, and
you going to get, you know, if you do
that, you're probably going to get a lot
of like early adopters. The people get
cuz like people are excited about AI
right now, so they're they're trying a
lot of stuff out. But, really to to
really have lasting value, you need to
figure out how to make your users win.
That's the hardest part. So, but it but
you know, it can be it can be amazing.
Um there's definitely lots of potential
there.
>> Yeah, it's just a such a great framing.
Like, and I mean, this is how you should
think about every feature. Like, does
this feature feature make my user win?
Like, does it improve their life? Does
it enhance whatever they're doing in the
app? You know, really thinking deeply
about how each of those features impacts
the user experience. Uh such a great way
to think about it.
>> You mentioned Opal for schools. I wanted
to to go deeper on that. Was this
something that happened somewhat
organically of students using it and
them requesting schools or did you like
strategize like hey, you know, this is a
great almost like B2B opportunity. We
can sell the schools. We can expand the
footprint. Like how did that come about?
>> Totally organic.
I had like fear that, you know, one day
maybe we would we'd work with colleges,
but working with schools like high
school was not something that I thought
about. But what happened was it started
last year. We literally got an email
from from a high school in Los Angeles,
Harvard-Westlake that essentially what
happened is they they had asked their
students, you know, basically
the state is telling us we can ban
phones. What should we do? And students
got back to them and said, well, you
know, we all or many of us are using
this app called Opal. We're using it on
our own, you know, no one's telling us
to do that, but maybe you should reach
out to them. So they had reached out to
us
to see if we could do something together
and and we found that, you know, it was
interesting actually to do that. And so
the way
what we did is we built Opal for
schools. What it is is it's a phone
policy that schools can use to help
their students focus and thrive. And the
way it works is the students download
the Opal app. And then when they walk
into campus, when they walk into school,
the banned apps are blocked on their
phone, but they can still access the
apps that are authorized, which is often
being able to text, you know, mom and
dad, but also educational apps. And so,
you know, for example, in some
circumstances, some case school would
say, you know, chat GPT is a is is it
can be used or, you know, this specific
kind of physics apps or this calculator
app. And the interesting part is that,
you know, when they leave school,
instead of, you know, just being handed
back their phone and being able to go
and and and just like binge uh all on
the social media, they still have the
app. And so, what we see is that a lot
of students are actually still using the
app after school to set up their sleep
schedule, to be able to do focus timers,
and study. And so, it's really kind of a
not a bell-to-bell solution, but a
bell-to-bed solution. It's kind of a a
full cycle. And so, yeah, we've tried it
with you know, one school and and now
we're actually kind of scaling it up
across uh the the states with many uh
high schools uh around the US. And so,
it's really become a very interesting
new area for us. Not only because again,
super aligned with our mission. We
really really like that. I think it's a
whole chapter we can open, but it's a
it's a much smarter way to actually do
phone policy rather than taking the the
the phones
uh away. We're actually kind of teaching
something to kids to get a tool that
they can use after school. And from a
business perspective, it makes sense
because it really helps position Opal
in in the family. Uh people talk about
it on the local community level as well
because every student uses it, so helps
a lot as well. But yes, it's a new kind
of
uh distribution for us that is uh is
super interesting and extremely
mission-aligned because, you know, we
need to make sure that uh education is
is still
uh and it continues to be uh an
important, you know, effective for
progress and and we can be a part of
that.
>> Another aspect to it, too, is that the
students will eventually graduate and
become professionals and want the tools
and no longer have it provided by the
school. So, it's also kind of like
growing up that next generation of pro
users who who are professionals who can
afford the the more expensive tier and
stuff.
>> I was very impressed. I remember my
college days when our college library we
there used to have PCs and then, you
know, they kind of did a
and all of a sudden they had
100% Mac everywhere. You know, this kind
of newest kind of beautiful uh beautiful
Mac that had been I guess that
practically given away
uh by Apple to kind of, you know, be be
uh be present in college. And yeah, I
think I think obviously, you know, from
a business perspective it makes sense to
make sure that the next generation knows
about the products and can use them and
can and and loves them. And I think that
in the case in our case, of course,
that's part of the value and it I think
it's also
aligned with the fact that we do need
the next generation to learn to build
these skills, to build healthier habits
in the previous generations. And so it
works it works together.
>> That's awesome. And and a great counter
example here and something you said uh
in passing is that the students need to
love it cuz like my my kids all have now
Chromebooks that they that the schools
hand out and they are terrible. My kids
will never buy a Chromebook. They like
beg to use my laptop. Yeah, we do have
an iMac home iMac. And and so if you're
going to go that route, it's like you
still have to have an amazing product
because that's what actually generates
the word of mouth, that generates it. I
mean, so much of what you've been
talking about is like having that core
product, the core brand, and that's how
it actually pays off. So
>> Yeah, I mean, it's been interesting you
have a B2B business because we're really
focused on people like B2C, you know,
like making sure that we have the best
possible app that's part of it. And it
turns out a lot of students are using
the app and actually love it on their
own. And again, it's not something that
people tell them to do or their parents
or their school. They use it on their
But we also happen to have this natural
extension of working working with
schools. But for for me, you know, the
compass is always how do we build the
best possible experience for the user,
make it fun, make it motivating, make it
make it as easy to use as possible. And
so as as long as we do that, you know,
we'll still
be able to make sure that Uh, the next
generation wants to use the app as well.
>> Are Are you able to share in in broad
strokes like what the the financial
arrangement looks like? Like Are you Are
schools actually paying per student for
this or are you just giving it away for
that eventual benefit?
>> We do charge schools for deployments and
using the service a per student fee that
is very competitive compared to
alternative solutions, but we do charge
we do charge schools, but for sure the
benefit of our business is expands way
beyond way beyond that revenue and
that's where we're able to kind of
charge cheaper prices to schools because
of that kind of other value that it
brings to the business.
>> Yeah, that makes it a whole new like
world for a consumer app founder to be
writing contracts with school districts
and like are you ramping up a sales team
or how are you handling that?
>> Yes, it's a new one that we have you
know someone excellent that's in charge
of the team Andy Bennett who is you know
head of
Opal for schools and he's we've been
talking to and in partnering up with
with so many different schools. He was
at South by Southwest EDU a few weeks
ago doing a presentation there with a
lot of educational leaders
talking to press and then we were
recently like front page news on
LA Times for actually the fact that we
now have you know one of the important
private schools in Los Angeles that's
using the product and and many others.
So yeah, it's a whole new world.
I think it kind of works though
very very well together with the
consumer product.
>> I I'd love to see it. It's It's so cool
to see consumer apps kind of expand
beyond that that the consumer base. You
know, seeing yeah, apps like Calm
Headspace years ago doing partnerships
with insurance companies and you know,
Calm I don't know if they're still doing
it, but you know, they had like a
section in CVS that was like the Calm
Shop like a few shelves where they had
like sleep gummies and like sleep masks
and things like that. So, it's really
cool when you think about these consumer
apps as a brand, as something bigger
than just the app.
There's just so many opportunities and I
think it's cool to see all the different
ways things that started as consumer
apps actually end up monetizing in so
many different ways and I I you know,
wouldn't have guessed schools, but
and it probably makes sense for for more
apps out there to expand that way if
they're really able to provide value to
students and school districts.
>> Yeah, I mean I think that when you have
an app and and people love it, you're
you're first of all, you're able to kind
of touch so many people, right? Like
millions of people literally, but more
than 10 million people downloaded Opal.
It's a massive amount of reach and
there's a lot of adjacents things that
you can do in new segments like we
talked about, but also new products that
you can maybe maybe sell to them as
well, right? But you know, for us really
the journey's been
the initial product market fit was on
professionals that are increasingly a
part of our still a big part of what's
kind of our customer base and then we
expanded to new segments with students
as we opened up
premium and then we have this kind of
new segment as well
going into
the education world and I think that you
know, when you look at screen time
overall and that's why I'm super
optimistic about you know, there's
competition, but there's also so much
space right with like 5 billion people
with a smartphone and every single
person needs a to help on managing their
screen time and building healthy habits.
But you know, you also see other
segments are possible that are you know,
more kind of health and lifestyle
segments
similar to what Oura and Whoop have done
in the
health metrics measurement, but you
know, screen time is also big big part
of people's health and so health and
lifestyle. So, this also massive massive
one and beyond that also think that you
know, as more and more research is
showing the impact of screen time on on
health, and impact of screen time on
productivity. You're also going to get
insurers that are going to take a big
part of this. You're also going to see
employers that are going to want to
build tools or or buy buy tools or
license tools for their their team. And
we believe that that's why it's so
important to actually build the most the
most loved and the most important brand
in that category because a brand can
travel. You know, when you have a great
brand, you can go from one segment to
another to another and build a billion
user products and billion user category,
which is what we're working on.
>> Yeah, you you've brought up brand a lot.
I wanted to to dig a little deeper in
that. What what are some of the key
things that you think, you know, make
the Opal brand the the touches in the
app, the the name itself, the design,
the the feel? Like, you know, how how
how do you classify or quantify
brand for Opal?
>> Yeah, I mean, there's a lot of things.
You know, we um the company started with
with a manifesto, actually, that I wrote
before like building a product. It was
really more like thinking about, you
know, what is um what is going on here?
You know, we've got uh
trillion dollar companies and they're
stealing people's attention, and they
build this technology that everybody
uses every single day. Technology is
really good, but
because of this business model and
because of the companies that are
building the technology used by by
people, uh we have the outcomes that we
know, which is, you know, overuse of
screen time. So,
you know, the manifesto is basically
saying, you know, we can can change
this, and we can actually design
products differently uh to benefit of
all the great stuff that technology
brings to people, all the good stuff,
but also like weed out the bad. And so,
we kind of started with that. And then,
you know, the product was kind of
consequence of that. And uh yeah, the
name, you know, is a is an important
part of our of our story. Opal is a
gemstone, and that's why you get all
these gemstones inside the app uh in our
marketing as well. And um and Opal is
actually also the the reason I chose
this name is that you know, I it would
it was striking to me that phones are
basically something that you touch all
day, every day, hundreds of times per
day.
And and so, you know, what are phones?
Phones are made of basically glass,
aluminum, all sorts of
different kinds of components and
they're electrically charged. They tend
they tend to be warm because of what's
going on. And as I was thinking about
like what is the exact opposite, you
know, from the tactile perspective to a
phone and and that that's where, you
know, gemstone kind of came up. Um and
Opal in particular, Opal is
is is a gemstone that's said to calm the
mind. In particular, blue Opal, it comes
in different variations. So, and it's
also very very precious gemstones.
That's the reason why, you know, the
name happened. So, it's not random.
There's a real reason why why it's Opal.
And then, you know, the the the whole
product experience
uh is centered around the fact that the
more you focus, the more you can unlock
these Opal gemstones with different
colors and different shapes. And we put
a lot of effort to kind of basically as
constant debates in our team
uh to basically make sure that that the
entire experience revolves around uh
around these gemstones. And so, that's
that's actually like one of the things
um the most loved interaction in the
app, which sounds completely uh you
know, stupid, but the most loved
interaction is that uh unlocking of that
stone like when you get granted that's
that that the new uh a new gemstone
because you've you've uh you've you've
passed the a new milestone you use the
app for a certain amount of days, for
example. Uh you get to kind of tap to
crack the the gemstone. And uh and
that's the most loved interaction. And
uh people really remember this, talk
about it, and really helps build the
brand because this is what the kind of
things that people remember. Um you
know, another example is we try to do
more things that are kind of unusual or
or companies might not uh do normally.
We have these stickers uh I want on my
phone here that says scrolling kills.
It's kind of like a PSA, you know,
public service now actually does not
mention Opal, which is
also controversial take, but we've
distributed thousands of them to our
customers, to users. We even bought a
this massive billboard in New York
last year with the message scrolling
kills because we want to be
we basically we want this message we
want this conversation to happen and we
want to be we want to be the company
that helps uh that helps make the these
changes. And so, that's another example.
And you know, there's many many small
smaller details
inside the app and how we do marketing,
partner with creators, partner with
different artists that helped I think
kind of build that brand and make it
strong.
>> I I love that gemstone interaction and
and I I was able to watch that video of
that interaction uh in in researching
all this.
And I I imagine that was very costly to
make. Like a lot of effort went into it
from artists and from programmers to
like get that interaction dialed in. But
I think more apps should find ways to
have those little magical moments, those
little touch points that like make it
feel special that like And I And And
this is maybe an example of kind of what
you're saying about, you know, using
technology for good. You know, here
you're you're almost dopamine hacking in
a way. It's like it's special. You know,
it's it's in a it's encased in a rock.
You don't know what it's going to look
like. You tap and then it breaks open
and it's like this reveal moment. I'd
imagine there's haptics and audio and
other things going on. And so, it is
kind of a dopamine moment, but it's like
you're you're using that as a reward for
them actually like being more present
and not using their screens as much. And
so, yeah, I think I think folks
listening to this should should think
about ways in their product to create
those kind of magical moments cuz it
really is so magical inside Opal.
>> Yeah, thank you. I appreciate it. I
mean, it's
tough to decide to invest in that kind
of thing because it's not really
measurable and it's not It is always
like 50 other things that you need to do
that seem more urgent,
bigger features, or bug fixes. And so,
it's kind of difficult to make the
decision to say, "Wait, I'm actually
going to invest like whatever, you know,
a few weeks building this thing and
doing it right." But in the end, that's
what people remember and that's what the
brand really is built on, those kind of
smaller details that feel unreasonably
sophisticated.
And uh but actually they they um they
really Yeah, it they bring magic to the
experience.
>> A few minutes ago you mentioned that
Opal had had over 10 million downloads.
You didn't say over 20, so I imagine
it's somewhere in the in the low, you
know, above 10 million.
Uh but then as we talked about it
earlier, you have over a million daily
active users, which kind of clued me in
that you got some like pretty awesome
retention. How How do you think about
retention and and how's that gone for
Opal?
>> We do have great retention. First, the
way the way we look at it is we need to
make sure that we can that that you can
do It's easy enough to kind of go on a
detox for 3 days and change your, you
know, kind of say, "Okay, I'm going to
put my phone away for 3 days." Which by
the way is a start. But it's really
difficult to do it on the on the long
run. And so, that's what That's why
retention is so important to us is
actually like to be able to change
habits in the long run. You really need
people to be able to stick around. The
way we think about it is it's definitely
like become the core. The only way you
can really grow your users and we we saw
how how important that is to to to have
organic growth. The only way you can
grow your daily users is basically
having great retention, obviously.
And so, it's really something that that
has been super important for us to to to
to crack. And so, you know, experimented
a lot, lots of tests to be able to
figure out what drives retention. It
starts from your know, the initial
onboarding. What do you actually onboard
people to? Yes, retention is a is super
important.
Um we're definitely today in the top
rank, I would say in in terms of early
retention. Yeah, they want to they seven
on par with or better than you know,
companies like apps like Duolingo or
Spotify or or Strava. And I think the
challenge for us is today is really how
do actually we've got this I would say
niche of people that are motivated
enough to build healthier habits with
digital technology. There's a few
millions we talked about a few millions,
but really what I'm focused on today is
I'm thinking about, you know, how do we
actually get the next 100 millions and
get this kind of billion user product.
And um and that really to me is about
making it way easier to take the first
step, making it way easier
um to get the benefits
without having to have so much
commitment. And so that's really, you
know, I I know in this podcast talk a
lot about what we've done the last year,
but I I'm spending a lot of time today
thinking about like what we're building,
you know, in the next in the next year.
And um and that's really what's what
we're thinking about today.
>> I'm going to quote you back to yourself
again cuz this is just so good.
Retention is the ultimate proof of
value. If a user comes back, you're
creating something real. If they don't,
nothing else matters.
>> Yeah, that's true. You know, it's uh you
and again, I think the reason I was
saying that is because if you look at X
today or Twitter, you know, you're
you're kind of like always you you're
talking about revenue, revenue, revenue
and and and people kind of quickly, you
know, growing their MRR which which is
great. I love revenue cats. I love
revenue too.
But, you know, I think like retention
really really is is the only way to have
like lasting value. It's the only kind
of real moat. And it's two different
things. It's it's one thing to be able
to convince someone to try out a product
and to pay for it at the beginning Uh
but it's another thing to to be able to
get people to actually stay for a long
run and and and create lasting value and
I think that you know, by the way, I
started you know, the Opal journey
started with just this first part really
like clearly at the beginning that's
what you should be doing but very
quickly it's also about how do you
actually build like lasting value and
the only way to to see that is retention
and and that's how you measure it. Yeah.
>> One of my colleagues was saying that
you know, there there are just too many
apps launching right now where kind of
onboarding is the product where there
isn't like a real product like it
doesn't actually even do the things it
says in onboarding and it's just all
about getting people to a hard paywall
taking their money but that's not I mean
that's just a short-term arbitrage.
That's not building a real business
because you know, they're not renewing
over time. The magic of subscriptions
and the magic of this business model is
that those cohorts stack over time is
that and I I imagine with the Opal it's
like you can look at those early cohorts
from you know, six years ago who are
still paying you money and have paid it
every month or every year
and when you start stacking those
cohorts and as you get to year six seven
eight it's just incredible
how that works if if you have that
retentive product and it really is just
that's how you build a real business
versus just like a short-term arbitrage
make some cash and then you know, watch
it all unwind.
>> And I think it's probably unpopular to
say because of
of what's what's going on right now with
you know, that the loudest voices are
more about like you know, cash grab
business but I I agree with you here.
Yeah, I think that's why you know, by
the way, I think AI is truly incredible
and again, you can build amazing
products that we haven't seen yet and I
I
I test so many but you can you can build
incredible products that really
serve your users in amazing ways but I
think that today a lot of hyper growth
in
are in the other category, which is
yeah, basically being able to quickly
create products that unfortunately have
no retention, you know, don't have a
brand, and
are not really delivering value to
users. And that's not very sustainable.
You need to make sure you you know, you
have a brand. You need to make sure you
have retention. You need to make sure
you are delivering value to users.
>> Yeah, such a great point. We we talked
about how you shifted a lot of user
acquisition to organic and are getting
so much more organic traffic. But I
imagine you still do a ton of paid ads.
And And actually, I know that for sure
because I do still get the the one Opal
ad that just crushes. It seems like your
phone is a nuclear-grade weapon aimed
against you.
Uh it's really kind of uh you know, a a
shocking and rightfully so. And it And
it's true. But any any tips for one,
finding those kind of creatives that you
can run for I mean, I saw the I first
saw it maybe a year or two ago.
Like it's still running. So, finding
those creatives that just crush and can
continue to to go. Uh and any other kind
of lessons and top learnings around paid
ads recently.
>> Yeah, I think you know, by the way, I I
hate to kind of always bring it back to
this, but I think it really comes back
to uh the brand. Like because we put so
much effort into building that brand and
building a product that is that brand,
we were able to get this particular
video I want to kind of tell you the
story. I don't think I've told it
before, but it's kind of kind of
interesting. So, um we uh we saw this
video actually that I think a friend of
mine sent a friend of mine sent me this
video. It was posted organically by
someone, and it got a little bit, you
know, a little bit of virality
organically. It was and and I saw the
video, and I was like, this this is
incredible because it looks like it's an
Opal ad.
But it's not. And so, you know, I I DM'd
the the person.
Um actually, it was
someone on my team, Maureen, who DM'd
this person and said, "I mean, we'd love
to maybe license this video." And and
the guy wrote back and said, "Actually,
like I use Opal and it was an
inspiration for right for making this
video." Um so it was kind of like
back full circle. Um he didn't do it as
an as a as an ad, but he said, "You
know, we kind of have to get people to
change and so we kind of need to uh and
he's a great filmmaker.
So, obviously, the video is amazing. And
you had no idea what how it performed,
so but we we did like ask him to if we
could use the video and he said, "Yes,
of course, as an ad." And so, basically,
there it already it is the organic video
with the Opal logo attached. That's it.
>> Wow.
>> And uh and it turned out to be pretty
pretty successful because I think it's
seen today like by dozens of millions of
people. And interestingly enough, it's
also not just an ad, it's a big part of
our brand. And also, it has value
outside of getting people to download
the app. So, we've heard a lot of people
that seen the ad and it
said they completely changed their
habits without even downloading the app.
So, it kind of also has its a life of
its own. But, um you know, since that
we've we've we've also partnered a lot
with various creators that have made
videos that are like just organic videos
we've either repurposed or, you know, we
commission new um creative videos. But,
I guess we have kind of unique unfair
advantage here, which is that a lot of
creatives, like actual people who are
filmmakers or, you know, designers,
actually are users of Opal because it's
a pretty popular amongst this group of
people.
Um so, I think we we get um
we get a bit of an unfair advantage here
of tapping into this community because
they they really care about this mission
and they really care about our product.
>> You you actually hired one of your
users, right? And and she now does
videos just for Opal?
>> Yeah, yeah, um absolutely. We actually
hired many of our users uh in our team,
but this particular one we uh are
accelerating our organic growth um in
many different ways and one of the ways
we do that is um we found this person
who was mentioning Opal in a video on
TikTok and and thought she was great.
And um and so basically we we hired her
and she's part of the team and um and
she's basically building a educational
media for us. Uh her name is Olivia and
so the channels are called Olivia
Unplugged and um and basically she's you
know educating people uh about
topics around screen time and focus but
it can go all the way from uh you know
how to make friends because people don't
know yet you know to how to make friends
anymore
uh offline to um you know how to how to
build a bedtime routine um and all of
these kind of different topics and she
does this in such an amazing way and
it's not you know an Opal brand account
it's like creator accounts um but that
that is powered by Opal and so Opal gets
mentioned in the videos and there's a a
link in bio but I think it works it
works really well because we went from
like zero to I think now 700,000
followers across different platforms and
millions of views in like a few months
and um and it's not just like it's not
just about the numbers because it's
really relevant cuz the content is
actually exactly like what the brand
wants to say and so it's very very
relevant.
>> Yeah, that's so cool hiring hiring so
many users and not hiring creators
uh were users and organically posting
content finding organic content
repurposing it as an ad so many cool
stories. We are we are coming up on time
but there's uh three questions I've been
asking every guest who come on so let's
uh let's get to that. Um the first one
is what's your biggest win of the last
year the experiment that performed way
better than expected um something you
implemented what what's your biggest
win?
>> Uh the biggest win is streaks.
Uh but it or not, we have our own
way of counting streaks. But
essentially, the more you focus with
Opal, the more you get a a streak. We've
also put a lot of effort, speaking of
brand, and like making making this
beautiful. Um so, the streak is
represented by this um this this small
frame,
uh which is, you know, not not like a
kind of emoji flame, but actually kind
of animated flame. And uh yeah, and you
can get, you know, beautiful Opal gems
towards what you reach kind of uh
different streak milestones. So, that's
that's the I would say the biggest win
in the last year to improve retention
and and growth.
>> Yeah, that's so cool. Streaks don't work
for a lot of apps. So many apps try
streaks. Uh but it's great to hear, and
it makes sense that it's landing for
Opal. I What What was your biggest fail
of the past year?
>> Yeah, I mean, what I would say is um
it's probably like So, we bought this
billboard
uh with that said, "Scrolling Kills" in
New York. And okay, I would say it's a
fail in the sense that we we
intentionally like didn't make
attribution really obvious. So, it it
didn't say clearly opal.app.com or
getting Opal. So, it's a fail in the
sense that no impact on downloads, no
impact on revenue. But that wasn't the
the point. Uh the point was really kind
of a brand statement. And so, actually,
it And just I think to finish on that,
we we signed a school uh in New York.
And And the moment that we signed the
the the deal in the
uh the head of the school actually
didn't tell us that
he saw the billboard, and because he saw
the billboard, he actually was more
comfortable signing. And so, you know,
it's kind of those things that are not
really directly measurable, but that do
make an impact. So, it's I would say
like a half a half failure here.
>> I I just Googled that while you were
talking, and when you Google "scrolling
kills," at least for me,
um pretty much everything that shows up
is uh Opal related. And you have uh
scrolling kills.us, scrolling kills Opal
saves. It's kind of cool to have this um
this kind of secondary tagline that you
can kind of like own almost like a
almost a trademark of like you you
created this phrase that you can just
put on a billboard and that even though
you probably like you said you didn't it
didn't impact downloads, but it created
an impression and then that impression
is tied to the Opal brand online, which
is so cool.
>> Yeah, I know. Thank you. I appreciate
it. It's It's definitely why we did this
and um we want to carry a message,
right? That's like already
uh that's important beyond just like
downloading the app, right? It's
actually just like something that
uh is important for society at large and
we kind of want to uh be be a part of
that.
>> Yeah, that's so cool. All right, last
question is fill in the blank. Growth
would be easier if
>> families got involved.
>> Nice.
>> So, you know, I think that every single
parent probably in the world today
is worried or concerned
uh about their children's screen time.
The problem today is that it's such a
conflict within the family. It's the
number one conflict source of conflict
uh between, you know, teenagers, kids
and and their parents. What we want to
do is we want to change that. And
instead of conflict like make this
something that people can do together,
make that a collaboration. And so, you
know, growth would be a lot easier if
families got involved because we would
be able to make sure that, you know, we
get one person in the family and then
everyone else in the family uh follow
suit. And so, and that's something that
we're working on.
>> Yeah, you're you're actually Did you
already launch or you're soon to launch
a family feature? Cuz you told me about
this last fall and I'm actually pretty
excited about it.
>> We're taking our time. We're taking our
time, but uh but it's it's coming. It's
coming uh very very soon.
>> Cool. All right, well, as we wrap up,
anything else you wanted to share? You
hiring? Looking for more creators?
anything else uh our audience can do for
you?
>> We're working on something really really
I say like a a big step change in the
whole product experience this spring
actually. Um and so yeah, the what the
audience can do is to watch out for the
next big update. It's going to be pretty
incredible. I'm really excited about it
and share any feedback that they have,
you know, to us
uh directly on the app. That's always
super helpful. Things that work, things
that don't work. Um this is uh this is
how we learn. This is how we grow. So we
appreciate that. And uh I really got to
got to talk David today. This has been
amazing. Thank you for the conference
also last week. Uh this has been this
has been a great conversation. Thank you
very much.
>> Yeah, thanks for thanks for joining me.
It's it's uh it's so fun chatting
through all this stuff and you have a
very different perspective, like you
said, than a lot of people in the
industry right now and I think it's uh
it'll be great for people to hear. So
thank you.
>> [music]
>> Thanks so much for listening.
If you have a minute, please leave a
review in your favorite podcast player.
You can also stop by chat.subclub.com
to join our private community.
>> [music]